Register of the Socialist Workers Party Records, 1928-2002
Wisconsin Historical Society
Socialist Workers Party Records, 1928-2002
Socialist Workers Party
Micro 596; Micro 816; Micro 993; Micro 1078; Micro 2015; Micro 2050; Micro 2086; AC 588; CB 131; M74-109; M81-206; M85-006; M92-173; M93-249; M2005-027
209 reels of microfilm (35 mm) and 2 films; plus additions of 146.2 c.f., 156 tape recordings, 40 disc recordings, 34 photographs, and 1 film
Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Records of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP), an organization which had its origins in the expulsions of Trotskyists from the Communist Party in 1928, and which has been one of the most prominent radical groups in the United States. The papers document numerous social struggles with which the party was involved, its political organizing, its internal policy and doctrinal disputes, and the lawsuit, Socialist Workers Party v. the United States Attorney General.
A portion of this collection is available only on microfilm. The films in this collection have been cataloged individually.
There is a restriction on access to and use of this material; see the Administrative/Restriction Information portion of this finding aid for details.
The records of the Socialist Workers Party are closely tied to the administrative organization of the party. The party operates on three levels: local organizations, the national office, and its international association, which, since 1940, has been informal. Almost all of the records in this collection have been generated in the national office.
On the local level the party provides for a variety of units of organization depending upon the size and vitality of the membership. The branch, the basic unit of organization, is the most significant body on the local level. Every member of the party belongs to a branch except for those members who reside in areas where no branch exists; they are known as members-at-large. In the past a branch has had between five and fifty members. Each branch elects its own leadership, the executive committee, which in turn elects an organizer and all local officers and committees. The executive committee directs activities between branch meetings but is ultimately responsible to the membership.
The party has several administrative bodies on the national level and it regularly convenes a national convention. The national leadership derives its authority solely from the national convention, the highest governing body of the party, where representatives of the branches assemble to formulate policy and elect a national executive. National conventions are held at least every two years. More frequent special conventions may be called by the national executive or on demand by branches representing one-third of the membership. The two bodies elected by the national convention are the National Committee (NC) and the Control Commission. The latter, which has one of its five members delegated by the NC, is less involved in the normal operations of the party. Its function is to carry out internal investigations in the interest of party welfare. The Control Commission takes no action but presents its findings and recommendations (depending on the circumstances under which it was convened) to the Political Committee, National Committee or convention. Although the Control Commission is a standing body, it is dormant unless convened by the Political Committee to investigate a particular dispute. The NC meets only a few times each year, and its meetings are known as plenums. Its size is determined by each new convention and thus it changes frequently. The main function of the National Committee is to develop policy which it formulates on the basis of the decisions of the national convention.
The Political Committee (PC) is responsible for day-to-day operations of the party organization. It is composed of members of the NC, traditionally those members who resided in New York City. The PC assumes a broad function as the central authority between plenums and it is authorized to speak and act in the name of the National Committee. All party organs and branches are under the supervision of the PC which meets whenever needed, even several times a week. Several subordinate leadership bodies report to the Political Committee. The Political Bureau and the Secretariat basically function as the PC. Moreover, at times it elects a secretariat to operate between its meetings.
The records of the Socialist Workers Party are one of the largest and most complete research collections at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin on left-wing politics in the United States, documenting not only the party's own tumultuous internal history, but also its relations with various other right and left wing organizations. Its value is further enhanced by the network of collections of related organizations and party leaders also held by the Historical Society.
Despite its size and research importance, the collection is by no means complete. Entire aspects of party functioning such as membership, finances, and the editorial preparation of its many publications are unrepresented. Some party records have been deposited at the Hoover Institution.
This collection was received in multiple parts from the donor(s) and is organized into 8 major parts. These materials have not been physically interfiled and researchers might need to consult more than one part to locate similar materials.
Part 1 (Micro 596, Micro 816, Micro 993, Micro 1078, Micro 2015, Micro 2050, AC 588, CB 131): Original Collection, 1928-1993
Part 2 (Micro 2086): Additions, 1994-2000
Part 3 (M74-109): Additions, undated
Part 4 (M81-206): Additions, 1967-1972
Part 5 (M85-006): Additions, 1928-2001
Part 6 (M92-173): Additions, undated
Part 7 (M93-249): Additions, 1953-1972
Part 8 (M2005-027): Additions, 1929, 1940-2002
Administrative/Restriction Information
The following portions of the collection are restricted for a period of 10 years after the date of creation, issuance, or publication of the materials: Minutes of Political Bureau, Secretariat, and other bodies elected by the Political Committee; National Office mailings; Local and District Internal Bulletins; and SWP Discussion and Debate Files.
Presented by Thomas Kerry, Socialist Workers Party (New York), Socialist Workers Party (Minneapolis Branch), Socialist Workers Party (Los Angeles Branch), George Novack, Library of Social History, Reba Hansen, The Militant via the Library of Social History, Bob Schwarz, Steve Clark, and Holbrook Mahn M67-374, M68-051, M70-099, M74-109, M75-540, M75-647, M76-046, M76-566, M80-075, M81-206, M84-030, M85-006, M86-116, M92-048, M92-173, M93-078, M93-249, M95-072, M97-184, M92-180, M92-182, M92-192, M2002-080, M2005-027
Contents List
- Part 1 (Micro 596, Micro 816, Micro 993, Micro 1078, Micro 2015, Micro 2050, AC 588, CB 131): Original Collection, 1928-1993, Micro 596; 185 reels of microfilm (35mm) and 2 films
  Included are administrative records such as constitutions, committee minutes; extensive files of internal publications; and correspondence with members and local branches. Other internal files document Pathfinder Press; the party's publication program; and schools, camps, and adult education classes. Additional files of press releases, campaign literature, and correspondence document the participation of SWP candidates such as Farrell Dobbs and Grace Carlson in national elections. Numerous files represent the legal cases in which the party was involved concerning civil rights, civil liberties, and academic freedom. Organizing work is reflected in correspondence and memoranda about the Black Panther Party, the Freedom Now Party, and the National Black Independent Political Party; files on the Alexander Defense Committee (South Africa), the American Committee for European Workers Relief, the Committee for Artistic and Intellectual Freedom in Iran, the Fair Play for Cuba Committee, and the United States Committee for Justice to Latin American Political Prisoners; and files on the National Maritime Union, the Teamsters, the United Automobile Workers, the United Electrical Workers, the United Steel Workers of America, and other unions. Information about the SWP's opposition to the involvement in the war in Vietnam is scattered throughout the collection.
  Also included are documents pertaining to predecessors of the SWP such as the Communist League of America, the American Workers Party, and the first Workers Party; to the Communist Party and left wing groups formed in opposition to the SWP such as the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party, the Sparticist League, Spark, the W.E.B. Du Bois Club, the Young Workers Liberation League, the National Alliance Against Racism and Political Repression, and the Maoist Revolutionary Communist Party; and to right-wing opponents of the SWP such as Lyndon LaRouche, Jr., Gerald L.K. Smith, and the Legion of Justice. The Original Collection is entirely available on microfilm. After filming, the original records were destroyed.
  Large portions of the collection such as the minutes and branch circulars, consist of material that was duplicated for distribution rather than the original documents from which these circulars were prepared. It is presumed that these original documents may have been retained by the Party.
  The Socialist Workers Party collection was compiled at the Historical Society over a period of many years, with each accession separately loaned for microfilming and the originals subsequently returned to the party. One result is that the collection microfilm has separate call numbers for its several portions. Individual items were filmed in the order in which they were received so that they could be returned unaltered. As a consequence, the order on the film is sometimes haphazard. In addition, reels 32-34 of Micro 596 were filmed without frame numbers though reels 32-33 were framed with Segment (folder) identifiers rather than frame numbers. However, beginning with the Johnson-Forest Tendency material, neither type of number exists, and the documents appear in the order in which they are listed in the contents list. Researchers are urged to rely on the contents list for access.
  The collection is arranged in 9 series: Administrative Records, Publication Records, Education Files, Election Files, Branch Correspondence, Activities and Organizing Records, Historical Files, Opponents Files, and Internal Discussions and Disputes Records.
  Administrative Records
  This series includes constitutions and minutes of the Political Committee meetings, sometimes called the Club Executive, as well as minutes from the National Convention and the National Committee meetings and plenums, together with minutes (for the 1980s only, however) of various leadership committees of the Political Committee. The documented leadership committees are the Political Bureau and the Secretariat, which appear to have functioned for the Political Committee, and the Organization Bureau, the Trade Union Bureau, and, after 1987, the Organization and Trade Union Bureau. The minutes vary greatly in detail, and lengthy documents and reports are often attached. There are also information sheets circulated to the National Committee, organizers, and the branches.
  Also included with the Administrative Records are files on the Control Commission, a national committee established in 1940 at Cannon's suggestion in order to maintain party security, investigate violations of party discipline, and make recommendations for official action to the National Committee. While the overall purpose of the Control Commission is difficult to discern from the records here, several documents hint at its function. Of particular use is the History File which contains opinions from Lenin and various SWP members on the need for party discipline, outlines of the commission's history, and materials on overall jurisdiction and purpose.
  The Control Commission files are subdivided into 1) commission history and 2) cases, with the cases being arranged alphabetically by name. It is unlikely that all discipline issues brought before the commission are represented here. Typical files include those of Elaine Carroll, who was charged with providing Minneapolis police with information about the SWP; Lydia Bennett (Beidel), who was accused of using the party to publicize factional activities when she held a social for members of the SWP and the Workers Party; and Al Duncan who was censured by the commission for striking a fellow party member.
  Several cases are represented by correspondence and background documents as well as by the commission's reports and recommendations. Since the commission held jurisdiction over all branches, much of this correspondence involves the logistics of arranging meetings and notifying the individuals involved. Unfortunately, many files are spotty and incomplete and several, such as the Special Investigations file and the files concerning Paul Jensen and Debby Leonard, fail to include the commission's decisions. Moreover, a few contain information on issues and individuals that the commission did not officially investigate, including Sylvia Caldwell, a personal secretary of Cannon accused of spying for the pro-Stalin GPU by the Workers League; Willie Reid, an African-American fugitive who escaped from a Florida chain gang; and Leroy McRae, who was involved in Mobilization for Youth, a publicly funded program investigated for subversive activities in 1964 and 1965.
  The circular letters are mimeographed items distributed by the National office to the local branches, to specific members or officers in the branches, or to specific branches. The letters deal with the operation of the party and were used to keep the rank and file informed on matters such as meetings, sale of bulletins; sales quotes, fund drives, and memberships. Often the circulars included issues that did not warrant inclusion in the bulletin.
  Also filed here is a group of membership statistics compiled by the party. The reports included not only numbers of members, but also data on membership by branch, by fraction, and by occupation. Except for 1945, the detailed branch reports from which these statistics were drawn are not included in the collection.
  Publication Records
  This series contains material directly related to the Socialist Workers Party's attempts to establish an independent press. In particular, the files concern the background and history of Pioneer Publishers, the leftist publishing house founded by Max Shachtman in the 1930s; Merit Publishers, which specialized in English and Spanish texts before evolving into Pathfinder Press in the 1970s; and The Militant, the longtime voice of the party. Aside from material relating directly to the establishment and administration of the party press, the files include a number of documents concerned with projects such as the party's speakers bureau which are indirectly related to publications. Also included here is an alphabetically-arranged library of SWP publications.
  The publication files are not the complete, organic records of any of the SWP's editorial and publishing operations, but instead a group of documents apparently selected by the party for preservation. Included are correspondence, many book lists and catalogues (some years only include photocopies of catalogue covers), promotional material, sample order forms, editorial and executive policy statements, and sales and distribution statistics. This section can be roughly divided into two distinct parts: first, administrative and background information, and second, records and documents concerning particular publications. The background and administrative records are further divided into two parts: general background and documents concerning the governance of the publication program. The background information includes a brief letter from Rose Karsner about the origins of Pioneer Publishers, extended correspondence concerning the establishment of Merit Publishers in the 1960s(?), and a short exchange of letters concerning Perspectiva Mundial, a magazine aimed at Spanish-speaking Trotskyists in the United States. Also here are the by-laws of the Militant and the International Socialist Review, together with a file (1961-1989) of the annual statements of ownership required by the U.S. Post Office.
  The policy documentation relating to the publication program consists of minutes for the four governing committees of Pathfinder Press which made decisions on what should be published, set style standards, assessed the progress of specific publishing projects, and monitored book sales and program finances. These records primarily date from the 1970s when George Breitman and George Weismann were leaders in the publication program.
  Following the files about background and administration, are documents arranged alphabetically by publication title. About the Militant there is extensive mimeographed correspondence concerning the ban placed on the newspaper by the Post Office during World War II and on the efforts to mitigate the effects of that ban. Similar documentation pertains to the Militant's operations in the immediate postwar years. There is little original correspondence here, although letters from Norman Thomas and Max Shachtman testify to their views on the attempted suppression of the Militant. Statistical reports and comparisons of various kinds document the paper's history from 1940 to 1990.
  The history of Pathfinder Press is documented by a run of catalogues, (some items being represented only by photocopies of catalogue covers), samples of book lists and order forms, promotional material, and sales summaries. The documentation for Pioneer Publishers includes a run of mimeographed promotional correspondence and statistical sales reports, as well as a collection of catalogues that run from 1935 to 1965. More useful than either the quantitative sales information or the catalogues, however, is a run of narrative reports that cover the period from 1940 to 1968. At the end of the file is miscellaneous material including correspondence of George Novack and Connie Weissman that pertains to the English language publication of Ernest Mandel's Traite d'Economic Marxiste, several items relating to the SWP's Trotsky publishing project, and an extensive file of tour schedules and reports, mainly 1973-1974, regarding YSA and SWP public speaking tours, and most notably the SWP (or YSA?) Speakers Bureau which sponsored a host of leftist speakers, such as Andrew Pulley, Peter Camejo, and Olga Rodriguez.
  At the conclusion of the series is a library of SWP publications arranged alphabetically by title. These titles have been included here rather than separating them to the SHSW Library, since most were intended only for internal distribution. Only a few titles require additional comment. The internal bulletins and discussion bulletins were intended to provide information to all levels of the party between the national conventions and distribution outside the party was specifically prohibited. Although several different titles are included Internal Bulletin, Discussion Bulletin, and Internal Information Bulletin), the distinction between titles is not always clear. The international information bulletins are similar in character, often consisting of translations of material from the bulletin of the International Secretariat of the Fourth International.
  Educational Files
  The Educational Records are arranged alphabetically by program. In general, these files document the party's attempts to establish a core of leaders well versed in Marxist and Trotskyist thought. The majority of the series relates to educational programs under the auspices of the SWP national office, although there is some documentation pertaining to educational programs operated by local branches. For example, an early course, Selected Readings in Marxism, is identified only as having been edited in Toronto by Maurice Spector in 1932. Also included in this series is an outline for a course taught by Albert Glotzer at a Marx-Lenin School in Chicago; announcements of courses, 1933-1934, offered by the Communist League of America; a 1935 administrative report of the International Workers School together with outlines of courses probably taught there by M. Abern and B.J. Field during the 1930s. The collection also includes the 1937-1938 bulletin of the Marxian Labor College in San Francisco and information and brochures pertaining to SWP retreats at the Mountain Spring Camp, the West Coast Vacation School, and the Midwestern Vacation School. The files on the Midwestern Vacation School and the Mountain Spring Camp contain information documenting the evolution of the SWP educational program. These files include correspondence between party members discussing the nature and purpose of the camps, as well as form letters distributed by the camp management, a few financial items, and advertising brochures.
  Aside from documents that specifically address SWP educational programs and policy, the educational files also contain general publications issued by the National Education Department such as study guides, handbooks, publications, and other basic tracts on Marxist education. Not all the documents are clearly identified, and it is possible some of the study guides may actually have been issued by local branches. Among the earliest items are a description of the basic training course, circa 1942, publications such as The ALP and Its Prospects (1943), Housing (1938?), Proletarian Military Policy (1940), and a bulletin of the New York Women's Committee. Study guides from the 1940s include a history of Russian Bolshevism, the ABC of Marxism, and What is Trotskyism? Several files also contain mimeographed course outlines issued during the early 1970s; the majority of the study guides and bibliographies, however, are undated. The file on the Oberlin Socialist Activists and Educational conferences includes printed programs from 1974 to 1989. (Programs for these conferences were occasionally issued with National Convention programs, which as a result, are also filed here.) Documents specifically tied to the party's Marxist Labor School, however, are disappointingly limited.
  The Summer School Files, which document the history of the National Education Department's summer school program and which primarily cover the period from 1964 to 1974, are divided into two sections: general correspondence issued by the national office and information about courses offered by individual branches. These files also include some interesting material on the evolution of the administration and function of the NED.
  Material on the SWP Trotsky School, the national training school for party functionaries, comprises nearly half the series. Here one will find correspondence (mainly of the 1950s and 1960s) concerning the development and management of the school. Included is an important 1944 memo drafted by James Cannon which foresaw the Trotsky School as the crux of the SWP's educational program. The school administrative files also contain letters of acceptance and rejection sent to interested applicants, lists of students selected to attend the school, fairly complete monthly financial reports, and a list of graduates. The course materials include outlines and study guides about Marxism and Marxist tracts such as Capital. Although they are not so identified, the 1954 and 1955 instructional files are thought to have been prepared by SWP leader Joe Hansen. Similar teaching materials document the 1959-1960 and 1961-1962 schools and several folders document the Leadership School, a related educational program instituted during the 1980s.